It was the only concentration camp in
history built exclusively for women.
Ravensbrook, Germany was less than 100
km north of Berlin near the town of
Fenberg.
The complex covered 9 square km, making
it the second biggest camp after Awitz.
It was established in 1938 by Hinrich
Himmler, the head of the SS and Hitler's
right-hand man. It was a segregated
internment camp designed to halt the
reproduction of the supposedly inferior
races and held prisoners of war and
women seen as criminals in the eyes of
the Nazis.
>> For what reason were we in prison? What
had we done?
>> That was the first shock of Ravensbrook.
From 1939 to 1945, between 130 and
145,000 women were deported from across
Europe to Ravensbrook, including some
8,000 French women. As many as 92,000
perished there. They were of all ages,
from fit young girls to ladies in their
60s and older. There were also infants.
>> That's something for which I've never
been able to forgive the Germans, the
children in the camps, the things we
saw.
Nothing like this had ever been seen
before. For the deported women,
Ravensbrook was the incarnation of hell.
The female Nazi guards behaved like
monsters.
>> You know, women are sometimes the worst.
>> Some of the older deported women used to
pinch their cheeks to give themselves
some color because after the roll call,
any women who were not in good shape
would disappear forever.
The French women were among the most
detested in the camp.
>> Oh yes, the howls and screams, the blows
from the offetin and even the SS, that
was part of everyday life. You should
remember that there were quite a lot of
us French women and we weren't very easy
to manage.
>> Medical experiments were carried out on
human guinea pigs.
>> I realized they had removed one of my
bones.
Nazi ideology called for the total
antilation of Jewish women and their
children with no distinction for age or
sex.
>> We were destined to disappear from the
surface of the earth.
>> Through the testimony of the last
survivors, illustrated by some
exceptional drawings made within the
camp by a French prisoner along with
digital reconstructions. This is the
story of Ravensbrook, the forgotten
camp.
I wish to declare the following.
>> May 1939, Germany.
>> The Second World War had not yet broken
out.
Nonetheless, the Third Reich was rolling
out a huge secret operation across the
whole German territory.
Hitler's trains and trucks crossed the
country loaded with prisoners who were
political opponents or Germans and
Austrians deemed unworthy of the Aryan
race.
On May 15th, one convoy arrived at the
edge of the small town of Fenberg, 84 km
north of Berlin.
On board were 860 German women and seven
Austrians.
They were the first inmates in the
Reich's only concentration camp
exclusively reserved for women and their
children, Ravensbrook.
The brand new camp at the time comprised
16 dormatory shacks, two workshop
blocks, the commandio guard quarters,
showers, kitchens, and the infirmary
called the Rivier.
The 9 square km site was ringed by a
wall 4 m high, topped with electrified
barbed wire.
As the roundups continued, the number of
dormatory blocks doubled to 32.
The Nazis also built a bunker containing
80 cells, one gas chamber, and a
building to house three crematorium
ovens.
Today, the dormatory blocks in
Ravensbrook have gone, destroyed by the
Nazis and later by the Russians when
they discovered the camp.
Only a handful of buildings remain.
the bureau of the commandant and the SS
officers known as the commandantu
the crematorium ovens
and some textile factory buildings
ravens was based on the model of dha for
example the layout of the shacks in a
rectangle was exactly the same in both
camps
The idea of Ravensbrook actually was
developed um by Himmler and Himmler
ultimately became the chief of all the
concentration camps. Uh so Ravensbrook
was his plan.
The head of the SS, the police and the
Gustapo Hinrich Himmler was strongly
attached to the idea of building a
woman's camp and he himself chose the
site at Ravensbrook.
Now why he chose that nobody knows
exactly but he he he knew the area.
Himler knew that area. A lot of these SS
uh officers used to love to go hunting.
They used to love to go out from Berlin.
They could get out from from Berlin in a
day. And this was an place with lots of
open spaces. Henri Hinri Himmler had
built the camp in a location that was
isolated and at the same time well
connected since it was close to Fenberg
station and a highway that connected
some major German cities.
>> It was a strategic spot in the middle of
the countryside close to a peaceful lake
because Himmler had some very particular
beliefs.
It was his strange ideology and
fantasies about rebirth of the of of the
German soul, the German land, the German
being in a purity.
Himmler was convinced that by assembling
these prisoners in the regenerative
forests of the Reich, the Aryan race
would be purified.
Up until 1937, women had been less
targeted by his policy.
We're dealing with a society that
imagines itself as Viral. And so there's
a very strong idea that women don't
think and therefore do not represent any
political danger, which explains why
between 33 and 37, the Nazis didn't do
anything much against women.
But from 1937 on, the wind changed. The
Nazis ruthlessly hunted down female
political opponents and communists and
later Jewish and Rahm women.
>> Hitler uh began to realize that um that
women were being rounded up in
increasing numbers and then they needed
to have a place for them. Uh and so he
devised this idea of a specific
concentration camp.
Today, very few survivors remain to
testify about their arrival in
Ravensbrook.
When the train came to a halt, we all
got off. We didn't know where we were.
Immediately the SS appeared accompanied
by their threatening dogs.
Move it.
And the dogs were dressed in the same
way. They had also gray uniforms on with
the SS on it.
And the guards were shouting away. Snow,
snow, snow.
>> We walked through the huge gateway,
which was very imposing,
>> and all we saw were the rows of blocks.
>> We were in a big assembly square where
we collapsed with fatigue, especially
thirst. Thirst is terrible.
>> It's worse than hunger for me anyway.
It's worse than hunger.
>> We saw two people come to water the part
of the square which we weren't in.
And none of us received so much as a
teaspoon of water.
We saw some very thin women file past,
dragging themselves along with shovels
on their backs. It was a terrible shock
because they were in such a state. It
made you wonder, who on earth are these
women? Where are we?
>> You never imagined you would become the
same.
>> These women must have done some
appalling things to be treated in such
way. They looked awful to us.
Some of them who were French called to
us, "You'll soon look like us."
And I admit that we thought this was
impossible. They wouldn't treat us in
this manner. We couldn't imagine what
was going to happen to us in the time
that followed.
>> I just turned 11 when I arrived at
Ravensbrook.
>> And so I had no idea what to expect.
>> For what reason had we been sent to
prison? What had we done?
>> We had no idea.
Lily Lenel Rosenberg, French, arrived in
Ravensbrook in 1943.
The reason for her incarceration,
Jewish.
Mai Jose Shambala Deovv, French,
deported age 21, arrived in 1943.
Reason for incarceration, member of the
resistance.
Jaclyn Flurry, French, aged 21 in 1944
when she arrived in Ravensbrook. Reason
for incarceration, resistance
membership.
Selma Vandere, Dutch, deported in 1944
to Ravensbrook, age 22.
Reason, resistance membership.
Wanda Kulkovich from Poland was the
first of these survivors to arrive at
Ravensbrook in 1940 at the age of 18.
the reason for her incarceration,
resistance membership.
All Europe was there. There wasn't a
country in Europe that wasn't
represented in Ravensbrook.
>> From 1939 to 1945, convoys arrived from
Poland, Austria, the Netherlands, the
Soviet Union, Belgium, France, and
beyond.
All these women followed the same
protocol on arrival.
>> They made us stand for 24 hours in the
square before sending us to the showers.
There
we had to undress fully and wait for the
Germans.
See,
>> then they took everything we had,
removing wedding rings, all that.
>> This scene and others were immortalized
in the utmost secrecy by Violet Lok, a
member of the French resistance during
her captivity here.
Her remarkable drawings acted as
evidence during the Ravensbrook trials.
>> We all had to strip naked.
We were so embarrassed. You know, at the
time we were very modest.
I had never seen my mother naked and she
felt very awkward in front of her sons.
Then you were looked at by doctors by a
doctor who I don't think had gloves on
or anything like that and in and um
investigated you sexually as well.
Um which was terrible.
>> We had to spread our legs and lean
forward.
Then they shined a torch underneath us
to check that we hadn't hidden any
valuables
like jewelry.
Then they gave us what was the only
possession of the deported which was
your bowl.
And we used to sleep with our bowls
because if you lost it you got no soup
and you would die much sooner.
>> They threw a dress to each of us which
we put on.
My name disappeared. I was no longer Mar
Jose Shambar Dealov. They called me
21706.
>> The deportiz then spent a fortnight in
quarantine before being put in the
shacks. Each woman was identified by a
piece of cloth, a yellow star for the
Jewish women, a triangle for the rest.
Those in the resistance were given red
ones.
We were turned into
pieces that the Nazis despised.
>> How do you withstand such a situation?
>> That was the first shock of being in
Ravensbrook.
>> The shock felt by the inmates as they
were stripped of their identity was only
the first of many.
From the third floor building known as
the Kandu, Max Kogal ruled the camp with
an iron hand until 1942.
appointed by Henrik Himmler. He was a
fervent Nazi, a notorious anti-semite,
and a cruel man.
In the initial rules at the Ravensbrook
concentration camp, there was nothing
about prisoners being beaten. It was Max
Kuggle who in 1940, encouraged by
Hinrich Himmler, asked that punishment
beatings also be applied to women.
love Kirgel realized there was no
bunker. He he didn't uh tolerate that.
He persuaded Himler that this was
necessary.
The bunker was always a place of
absolute horror for all prisoners.
The lower levels were the scenes of
torture, of beatings.
They were held in solitary confinement
in darkness with no food.
>> To run the camp, Kogal had under his
command some 50 SS troops and 55 female
guards. These were prestige posts, well-
paid for German women of modest
background. They were known as the Black
Crows.
>> From the moment they put on their
uniform, suddenly they were transformed.
It took around two weeks for a new guard
to become as brutal and as violent as
the other guards.
>> It was forbidden to look the Nazi guards
in the eyes.
When they took the roll call, we had to
have our heads lowered like this.
>> You quickly got used to being struck and
slapped. Blows to the head, too.
You know, women are sometimes the worst.
>> The female violence remained more
intensely scored in the prisoners
memories than the violence of the men
because it was unexpected.
Whether French resistance members,
Polish or German,
or women deported for racial motives,
for all the first torture was the roll
call. Four times a day, the prisoners
were counted in the central square
covering two square kilm.
>> The first blast of the siren, which
governed everything, was the wake up at
3:20 a.m. We would go and stand outside
and stay still in this position. you
weren't allowed to talk with the women
next to you.
>> The number of prisoners counted had to
correspond to the guard's list. For
example, if a woman had escaped, the
whole camp was left standing for hours
until she was found.
The women would wait here at 20° below
freezing in winter and in 30° heat in
summer. It was real torture.
I can still see some of the older
deported women, those who were sickly
who would pinch and slap their cheeks
during the roll call.
To begin with, I wondered what this
gesture meant.
I quickly realized they were doing this
to put some color in their cheeks
because when roll call was over, any
women who were not in good shape were
taken aside and they would disappear
forever.
>> Among the persecutors, three names have
gone down in history. Joanna Longafeld,
head guard until 1942 and the first head
of the women's camp in Awitz.
Maria Mandel who took over from Joanna
Langfeld at the women's section of
Awitz.
And Dorothia Bins, known as the
beautiful [__] the last headgard of
Ravensbrook. She took part in the mass
killings that took place there.
>> Bins benz
was an extremely brutal woman who
regularly struck people.
I was once beaten to the ground simply
because I put my hands in my sleeves
when they were freezing.
>> She was very much a kid who was very
troubled herself. She was a blonde. She
was pretty. She was attractive to men
and obviously she had innate inside her
some fairly sadistic tendencies which
the camp encouraged and brought out.
Officially, Doroththa Bince and her
fellow guards did not have the right of
life and death over prisoners, but they
often killed with their bare hands or
kicked people to death. Their
accessories were clubs and dogs.
>> Himmler had worked out that with one
dog, they could save on two or three
extra guards.
Himmler believed that women are
naturally afraid of dogs. So they were
used on a much wider scale as part of
the guard apparatus in concentration
camps for women.
To keep the women guards happy, they
lived in comfortable houses and would go
ice skating in winter and boating in
summer.
They frequented the SS soldiers and
would sometimes form intimate
relationships with them. When they left
the camp, where these men and women had
committed the worst horrors, they had to
give the impression that they were going
home like any office employee.
>> 50 m from their villas, the inmates
observed them.
>> We knew that they ate well. They had
boots. They had
we had nothing. We were in the cold.
>> They were well equipped, warmly dressed,
that's for sure.
>> The German, Polish, and Dutch women
interned in Ravensbrook, whether
political prisoners, prostitutes, or
those of Jewish origin, were all put in
dormatory blocks.
Each block which contained up to 200
inmates was divided into two symmetrical
parts. In each wing there was a
dormatory and common room with latrines
and a washroom in the center.
>> There were three of us per bunk and a
bunk was about 70 cm wide. In other
words, the width for one person. But
there were three of us.
So you can perhaps imagine what life was
like in those conditions.
>> We were like sardines.
>> Deprived of all humanity, the inmates
were condemned to a slow death. It was
Hitler's will.
But killing the prisoners was not enough
for the Nazis. They had to see them
suffer.
There was always a hierarchy amongst the
prisoners because of course Himmler was
a master of the art of divide and rule.
>> The Nazis knowingly involved the
prisoners in the working methods of the
concentration camps deliberately to
provoke antagonism between them.
They also planted spies in the blocks to
know what was going on inside and to
maintain control.
Indian blocks.
>> The SS didn't have enough staff or
guards to keep control on their own. The
prisoners had to do it themselves.
There's no doubt that if nobody had
agreed to collaborate with the Nazi
management system, these camps wouldn't
have been possible to run.
At the same time, victims and
persecutors, so-called capos, emerged in
the men's camps in the mid 1930s and
soon made their appearance in
Ravensbrook, where they were known as
Blovas.
One nationality that had been present
since 1939 gradually imposed itself over
time in these strategic posts, the
Polish.
>> Polish women were the most widely
represented nationality in Ravensburg.
Around 140,000 went through the camp.
>> They had good knowledge of the German
language,
>> so they had more chance of obtaining
these posts.
Many Polish women were capos. They
wouldn't tell you this, but Polish women
were not wellliked in the camps.
They worked for the Germans, especially
the
in general they were not very kind.
>> Some people even have appalling
recollections of these capos.
>> Through their dedication to duty, some
Polish inmates even succeeded in winning
the respect of Joanna Langfeld,
Ravensbrook's head guard.
She admired the Polish for their
nationalism and their patriotism.
However, as a good national socialist,
she had no pity for the Jewish
prisoners.
She was anti-semitic and would pick
these women in 1941 to send them to
special centers where they carried out
the extermination by gassing certain
female prisoners.
If there was a hierarchy in the horror,
the worst treatment in Ravensbrook was
reserved for Jewish women.
Jews had been present in the camp since
1939 and accounted for 15% of the female
population there.
From 1944 on, thousands of Jewish women
were sent there from Awitz or else
deported there directly on their own or
with their children. both girls and
boys.
>> The only children who were deported were
Jews and Roms.
>> We were destined to be eliminated from
the surface of the planet.
>> On the night of October 27th, 1943,
Lily, aged 11, was sleeping peacefully
in the family apartment in Rube,
Northern France, when she heard the
boots of the SS in the stairwell.
This date remains indelibly imprinted in
my mind
because it was my mother's birthday.
>> It was on that night that the
Feljandarie came crashing into our house
in the middle of the night at 3 in the
morning. They marched up the stairs,
banging on the doors. We were woken with
a start.
>> The whole family was arrested.
>> The reason given was that we were of
Jewish origin.
That was our crime.
>> Lily was then sent to Germany with her
mother and two brothers aged nine and
three.
Her father was sent to Bkenvald from
where he never returned.
In Ravensbrook, Lily met the same fate
as thousands of other deported Jewish
women.
They were kept separate from the other
prisoners. They were given less breaks
from the slave labor. They were slurred
by the guards. They were called Jewish
[__]
And many of the prisoners probably felt
a certain anti-semitism towards them as
well.
Whether due to overcrowding or simple
Nazi pragmatism, it is hard to say why
some Jewish women were sent to
Ravensbrook rather than elsewhere.
It is also hard to say how many Jewish
women and children died in Ravensbrook.
But one thing is sure, even before the
construction of a gas chamber at the
camp, their chances of survival were
much lower than any other group in the
camp.
The Nazis, according to their whim,
would sometimes pluck a child from one
block or another, and that child would
never be seen again. Every evening when
she returned from work, Mama anxiously
wondered, "Will I find my little
children waiting for me?"
>> Political prisoner was much better. Mind
you, some many of them were killed or
died just the same, but not as
automatically as when you were Jewish.
There was no question about not being
sent to ours.
Selma Vanderpair was 22 when she was
deported to Ravensbrook. A member of the
resistance, she hid her Jewish identity
until the liberation, as did Denise
Verete, the sister of Simonve.
I was afraid of that all the time. Yeah.
I pushed my real identity away as much
as possible. I was scared that I was
going to talk in my sleep.
I was scared all the time about that.
Yes. Yes.
>> The Jewish were always singled out um
for worse treatment than the rest of the
prisoners. Um and this went through
right till the very end.
And yet, amidst the nightmare of the
Jewish women's block, there were rare
moments of happiness.
There was a Polish lady who was amazing.
And when there weren't too many SS
around, she gathered us together and
told us, "Sing something."
For those few minutes when we were
singing, we thought we had already left
the camp and were perhaps at home. They
were exceptional moments.
>> Gaul, come quick and save us from here.
Gaul, I beg you, if you don't come, we
will all be done for.
>> D, do not forget us.
As the population in Ravensbrook
continued to grow, numbering more than
2,000 prisoners, Germany was making
territorial gains in an ever more brutal
war.
Vermached tanks entered France.
The French capitulated. Paris was
declared an open city.
Soon after, women began joining the
resistance. Among them was Jacine Flurry
who was 17 at the time.
>> I'm from a family who objected strongly
to the occupation. The whole family
became active in the resistance
movement.
>> Jaclyn joined the defense of France
group. One of her missions was to carry
the movement's clandestine newspaper
from Paris to Versailles.
>> Seeing the swastika flying over the chat
de Versailles was unacceptable for us.
Totally unacceptable.
And without any need for discussion, we
thought we had to do something against
this occupying force.
>> At the end of June 1944, she was
arrested in her home by the Gestapo
after 4 years of resistance activity.
Only her brother managed to escape.
>> My father, mother, and I were arrested
in late June of 44 and taken to Fen
Prison.
We were taken there in a blacken
which I think was familiar to all
resistance members who were arrested.
From friend prison, Jaclyn was sent to
Ravensbrook, the most frequent
destination for those deported from
occupied France under repressive
measures.
Among the French resistance members in
the women's camp along with Jaclyn, some
became well-known figures like the
ethnologist Gaia Tilly,
Jeanv de Gaulle, the general's niece,
and Denise Vane, the sister of Simonve.
But this was only part of the picture.
>> You had sort of French aristocrats. You
had countesses mixed up with kind of
French prostitutes, with French lawyers,
with with all sorts. Uh, they were all
mixed up.
>> The French women were among the most
hated in the camp, despised by the
Slavic inmates who found them too
precious.
>> When the French women found out some
Polish women were due to be shot, they
would come to see us and say, "Give me
your scarf. You won't be needing it now.
The Slavs, they're physically tougher
and the French were physically very weak
right from the start. They were much
more delicate.
So the French start dying very quickly.
>> The French women who arrived in
Ravensbrook later than the other
nationalities were assigned the hardest
tasks.
>> This very quickly left its mark on us.
We were soon just skin and bone since we
hardly ate anything. You wither away
very quickly.
>> You unload coal wagons for 12 hours.
You get home. You've got nothing to
change into. You only have water. You've
got nothing to wash with. You're in a
terrible state of fatigue.
And the next day, you're awoken at 4:30.
You head off for another 12 hours of the
same work.
And when the road was finished, they
tore it up to start again.
>> Can you imagine living like that?
>> Do you think that's enough?
>> The Nazi guards also hated the French
women and never appointed them as
we said.
>> Oh, yes. The howls, the screams, the
blows from the offetiran
and even the SS. All that was part of
everyday life. You should remember there
were quite a lot of us French women and
we weren't very easy to manage.
The Germans also had a very firm idea
about France and saw the French as
hereditary enemies of Germany.
>> The French women were not trustworthy.
We often heard them say, "You French
women, you're very poor workers."
>> If they only knew how delighted we were
to hear that, then maybe they wouldn't
have said it so often.
But we were very happy about that
because we were doing it deliberately,
obviously.
June 1941,
Germany broke the German Soviet pact and
attacked Russia.
To execute his plan, Hitler mobilized
millions more soldiers.
The Nazi war machine depended on the
output of German industry more than
ever.
They had to produce more and more
military equipment ammunitions and this
led to companies involved in war-
rellated production to set up on an
increasingly large scale as part of the
concentration camp system.
From 1942 onwards, companies such as IG
Farbin, Porsche, Balszen, Bush, and Opel
began to rely on the concentration camp
mechanism.
Seamans moved into Ravensbrook.
Its vast factory made up of 16 workshop
blocks used the deported women as labor.
>> The inmates would be leased and made
available without wages
by a private company which paid the SS a
variable sum.
Germany would become an immense war
factory and deportizes formed a
workforce which cost nothing.
>> When the deport died, they were
immediately replaced.
>> The women deported to Ravensbrook were
particularly useful. Himmler believed
they had smaller hands so could carry
out more precise and meticulous tasks.
>> We were quite simply slaves. No two ways
about it.
Between the slavery, torture, and secret
transports to the gas chambers,
Ravensbrook in 1942 was a hellish prison
regime.
But the Nazis would sink yet further in
the horrors they perpetrated.
In 1942, Hitler lost one of his key men.
Reinhardt Heddrich, chief of the Reich
main security office, died as the result
of an ambush in Prague.
The SS doctor Carl Ghart was dispatched
to save him in vain. Hitler was furious.
It was Carl Ghart who decided on the
treatment, but his approach was
criticized.
If he had used the new antibacterial
drug sulfonomide, Hadrish could have
survived.
To preserve his reputation, Gart set out
to demonstrate the ineffectiveness of
sulfanomide, a forerunner of antibiotics
on gangrine.
And Ravensbrook would be the arena of
his medical experiments.
These were carried out in the Rivier,
the infirmary block,
a double building covering 1500 square
meters, connected by a corridor
comprising 20 rooms, including seven
wards for the hospitalization of
inmates, an operating theater, an
examination room, and offices.
That day, a group of inmates were
presented to a college of Nazi doctors.
The women were all in perfect health and
they were Polish.
The Nazis considered Jews as a sort of
subhuman.
So any experiments on them would not be
conclusive when applied to Aryans.
So they had to use human subjects that
they saw as closer to Aryan, made up of
Polish, a subcategory in terms of Nazi
ideology,
but nonetheless a form of humanity
closer to the German.
>> Since its creation in 1939, the
infirmary in Ravensbrook was not like
any ordinary hospital.
In general, when anyone went to the
river, it was to die.
I shared a bunk with the woman who had
died in the night and another who was
coughing up blood.
But in 1942, the diabolic mind of
Hinrich Himmler came up with the idea of
using inmates at Ravensbrook as human
guinea pigs, prefiguring Mangallay's
work in Awitz.
Carl Ghart was put in charge of this
mission.
The concentration camp system offered SS
doctors subjects in this case human
beings who were seen as raw material
that could be used in a whole range of
medical experiments.
>> One of these guinea pigs survived.
Wanda Kulik Rosvich. We tracked her down
to the Polish capital Warsaw.
On that day, they took me into the
operating theater in a wheelchair.
>> I had no idea why I was being taken
there.
They injected us with a liquid.
We were laid down,
>> completely drowsy.
We didn't know what was going to happen
to us.
>> We were in good health.
They were the most horrific mutilations
that were carried out on legs primarily,
but not only on legs, where they were um
they their bones were deliberately
broken and um their muscles were crushed
and they were infected deliberately with
gang green and with other incredibly
infectious
diseases.
The subject had pieces of glass and
splinters of wood pushed into open
wounds
and were injected with diseases like
typhus and gas gangrine.
Gart's experiments not only violated
every ethical code, but they
demonstrated nothing.
Disoriented and semiconscious, Wanda was
unsure how many days and nights she
stayed in the revier.
I realized they had removed one of my
bones.
Our legs stank like rotten fish.
>> The stench was terrible.
On top of that, it was awfully hot.
>> All in all, it was horrendous.
In the eyes of the Nazis, we weren't
even human.
In total, 86 deportes, including 74
Polish women, were used as human guinea
pigs in Ravensbrook, as these
clandestine photos show.
23 would die as a result of these
experiments.
Having had nerves, muscles, or bones
removed, the survivors tended to hop
around and were given the cruel nickname
of rabbits. Those
young Polish women walked with
difficulty. They had wounds on their
legs, and we learned from fellow inmates
that they had been used as guinea pigs.
It was more than a shock, it was
unimaginable,
not only inhumane, but we'd never even
thought such a thing could happen.
>> One year later, in February 1943, the
Nazis suffered a crushing defeat in
Stalingrad.
They were losing ground. The Allies
landed in Italy.
Yet Ravensbrook seemed cut off from the
rest of the world.
And the rabbits were still undergoing
the most inhuman torture and executions
intensified.
Then in March 1943, the mutilated
inmates attempted the unthinkable.
>> We organized a sort of march of the
infirm.
We wanted to see the command.
>> We wanted to tell him that the prison,
the operations, the firing squads,
it's all getting to be too much. Don't
you think
>> the response of Fritz Surin, the camp's
new commandant, to these grievances was
to issue orders for four of the
protesters to be executed. The human
guinea pigs continued to rail against
the Nazi machine. The head guard, Joanna
Langangerfeld, came to their defense.
>> Joanna Langangerfeld, found out that
these women were due to be executed
because they had been summoned by her
hierarchy.
That was when she picked up the phone
and called the commandant.
>> Langfeld was herself stripped of her
functions for insubordination.
After the war, despite her involvement
in the killing of Jewish women, some
Polish women helped her escape the
prison where she'd been incarcerated,
thereby avoiding trial.
In Ravensbrook, despite Langfeld's
intervention, on February 4th, 1945, the
Polish women were ordered not to leave
their block. Their execution was
approaching.
>> They had to be killed because they would
be the living witnesses, the living
evidence of this war crime.
The rabbits probably would have been
killed if other inmates had not risked
their lives to save them.
A general roll call was announced.
All the prisoners were assembled in the
square.
And they had to stand there until guards
identified them.
One inmate created a diversion, shouting
out that there was some bread available
somewhere.
The starving prisoners all rushed to
that place, sparking chaos, which
allowed the Polish women to hide.
>> They were hidden in the roof of the
blocks. They were hidden in the hospital
block and they were pretended to be dead
or or they were disguised or they were
dressed up in in in other clothes.
And they were moved at night. If if it
was felt that the guards knew where they
were, then the prisoners came together
and sort of moved them from block to
block.
>> The prisoners hid the rabbits in other
blocks. They did, for example, swap
their prisoner numbers for those of
inmates who were already dead.
They were helped by the whole camp. The
whole camp tried to save them. and
what's more succeeded.
>> Despite the incessant hunt that
continued up until the liberation of the
camp, the Nazi guards never put their
hands on the rabbits in what was a
powerful act of resistance in the
history of the concentration camps.
1944, German forces were teetering all
over Europe.
The Reich was collapsing.
And yet this was when the Nazis would
generate even more victims with the mass
deportation of Jews to carry out their
project of extermination and the
dismantling of resistance networks. So
far, the Nazi doctors at Ravensbrook had
managed to control the occasional
pregnancy by performing abortions on any
deport who arrived pregnant. But now the
inmate population was exploding.
they simply couldn't carry out abortions
at the rate that was necessary to stop
babies being bought in the camp. So this
extraordinary uh idea was arrived at
which was that we will let the babies be
born
and then we'll let them die.
Fritz Surin started the Kinder Zimmer a
ward for children to which French
resistance member Mar Jose Shan Deov was
assigned as a medical student.
>> I entered this room and was appalled to
find newborns piled up on the beds where
they were being kept.
They looked like little old men. It was
horrific.
>> That was one thing for which I could
never forgive the Germans. the children
in the camps, the things we saw.
>> The technique of starvation had already
been tried by the Nazis
in Ravensbrook. It was applied to babies
and their mothers.
>> The food was so appalling that the state
of their bodies was just not producing
any breast milk. So that's an added
torture that not only have you given
birth to this baby, but you then can't
feed the baby.
>> So once again in Ravensbrook, an act of
resistance was organized. The Deep
Ortiz, who still had any milk, often the
ROM women who were more robust,
breastfed babies other than their own.
It was an act of desperation.
>> In Ravensbrook, I saw comrades who died.
There were executions, but for me, the
worst was the Kinder Zimmer.
With the advent of the Kinder Zimmer in
1944, Ravensbrook had sunk to fresh
depths of horror.
>> That violence was part of a very
particular stage in the war. A time when
the mass murder of anyone who could
constitute a danger began.
>> The Nazis wanted to take their murderous
ideology regarding the supposed inferior
races to its grim conclusion and at the
same time silence the witnesses and
victims of their crimes.
Jermaine Tillion who uh the French
prisoner who wrote about this said it
was lashas.
It was lash. They were hunting them down
like animals. And that's was the last
days of Ravensbrook.
In 1943, the Nazis had already built
three crematorium ovens in Ravensbrook
to burn the bodies of women killed by
shooting or injection or who simply died
due to the conditions.
To step up the pace of killing, the
extermination now took place in the
camp's gas chamber.
Here, from the start of 1945, the Nazis
packed in up to 180 people at a time.
None of the inmates were ignorant of
what was going on there.
>> There were several ways of killing
people. Of course, I was that scared to
go to the doctor because if you were
going to be sent to the river that they
might take might inject you and that's
how people died and were taken to the
cremation.
>> Mama tried to shield us from death. It
was sometimes present, but you know, you
can hide it from a little child by
pretending the person is asleep or
saying they went to the hospital to be
treated.
So when a dead person was removed, you
didn't realize.
>> We knew our fellow inmates. We knew
their real names. And when they died,
they would tell us, "If you ever get
back home, tell them how I died.
At the time, I thought a lot about
France because I thought I'd never see
it again.
>> Between January and April 1945, in just
3 months, nearly 6,000 women and
children died in the gas chamber at
Ravensbrook.
June 6th, 1944.
While the Nazis continued the mass
murder in Ravensbrook, the Allies landed
in Normandy.
But in the Reich's other territories,
Poland, Austria, Germany itself, the
liberation was still a long way off.
>> When we heard about the D-Day landings,
we said to ourselves, "We're not going
to spend another winter here.
>> But unfortunately, there was lots of
fighting. It took a lot longer than we
had hoped. It was interminable. We had
to hang on to the end."
The deportiz had to wait for long months
during which millions more fell victim
to the Nazi killing machine.
Awitz was liberated on January 27th,
1945.
Bookenwald on April 10th and Ravensbrook
on April 30th by the Red Army.
>> Some of the Russian commanders were
obviously horrified by what they saw and
did everything they could to help. There
was also a very dark side to the
liberation because of course the Russian
Red Army was notorious for rape of
women.
>> Among the ranks of the prisoners who
were finally freed was Ma Josev, a
French resistance member who had spent
two years in the camp.
>> The French women all sang the Marseilles
at the top of their voices. It was
incredible.
Lily Lener Rosenberg was transferred in
early April 1945 to Bergen Bellson.
Having been liberated, she returned to
France with her two little brothers. She
was reunited with her mother later.
>> What revenge over the Nazis? And it's
true. It's a kind of revenge. How else
can you explain that three little
children returned? That a child aed
three and a half survived.
French resistance member Jaclyn Flurry
and her mother avoided the death marches
before returning to France and to the
reception center for deportiz at the
Lutessia Hotel in Paris.
There were lists pinned up in the lobby
as far as I remember and we were asked
lots of questions.
It was very hard. It wasn't just we're
home that's great. Not at all.
And then the following morning they gave
you 10 Franks and a metro ticket and
that was it. You at home.
>> Piecing oneself back together having
survived Ravensbrook in a France that
wanted to forget was certainly no easy
task.
>> The trials which took place from 1946 to
1950 did however allow certain women
who'd been in the French resistance to
tell their story.
I knew the names of the commandant and
the doctors at the camp.
>> So after the war, I testified against
them.
>> In principle, I am against the death
penalty. But I thought it was quite
appropriate that those in charge at
Ravensbrook were executed.
>> In 1947, Carl Gart was sentenced to
death, having been found guilty of
murder, war crimes, and crimes against
humanity.
The commonant Max Kogal was arrested by
the US Army but committed suicide in his
cell in 1946.
Fritz Surin was sentenced to death and
shot in 1950.
The guard Doraththa Bins was executed in
1947.
Yet despite the trial and its
singularity, the Ravensburg camp long
remained a footnote in the history of
the war.
The people who wrote write the history
are usually men and men were simply not
interested. Male historians were not
interested and indeed most of them are
not today interested in Ravensbrook.
They showed extraordinary ignorance
about Ravensbrook.
The prosecuting lawyer who was actually
a British barristister trying to explain
Ravensbrook to the judges described it
as that he said he had to understand
this not just as a crime against against
him but a crime against women because
they were very specifically crimes.
>> Fortunately, the precious accounts of
the survivors still resonate notably the
celebrated writings of the French
resistance member Jamine Tillung.
I owe the fact that I survived first and
foremost to good fortune, then to anger
and the will to expose these crimes, and
lastly to a coalition of friendship
because I had lost the visceral desire
to live.